[{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"1. In Welsh myth, one of these creatures uses special forks to prop his eyelids open, and refuses to marry his daughter Olwen to the hero Culhwch [“KILL-hwick”]. One of these creatures is killed by Heracles after he steals the cattle of Geryon. According to legend, one of these creatures named Benandonner fought Finn MacCool on a basalt formation in Northern Ireland. A harp that plays itself and a goose that lays golden eggs are stolen from one of these creatures, causing him to shout “fee-fi-fo-fum, I smell the blood of an Englishman!” For 10 points, name these creatures, one of whom is killed in the story “Jack and the Beanstalk.” ","answer":"ANSWER: giants "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"2. Walter Pater described one of this artist’s subjects as a “vampire” who is “older than the rocks among which she sits.” A scroll reading “virtutem forma decorat,” surrounded by a laurel and palm leaf, is painted on the reverse of a portrait by this artist. This artist used red chalk for a work believed to be his only self-portrait. This artist of Ginevra de’ Benci painted Cecilia Gallerani holding a weasel in his Lady With an Ermine. His best-known portrait depicts a winding road behind the subject, who is lacking eyebrows. That portrait, known as La Gioconda, utilizes sfumato to create its subject’s enigmatic smile. For 10 points, name this artist who painted Lisa Gherardini in his Mona Lisa. ","answer":"ANSWER: Leonardo da Vinci [accept either underlined portion] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"3. This novel ends with the protagonist stammering “Me? Me?” in response to her lover’s statement “you your own best thing.” In this novel dedicated to “sixty million and more,” Amy helps the protagonist give birth to a baby on the banks of the Ohio River. A man with a “tobacco tin” heart comes to visit this novel’s protagonist at her “spiteful” home on 124 Bluestone Road. Denver and Paul D try to help the protagonist of this novel come to terms with her memories of Sweet Home plantation. Sethe is haunted by the ghost of her dead slave daughter in, for 10 points, what Toni Morrison novel? ","answer":"ANSWER: Beloved "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"4. This element can form a polyatomic anion solely consisting of 29 atoms of this element. When dissolved in a strong acid, this element turns into a bright blue paramagnetic solution. Sodium thiosulfate is often used in a type of titration that is named for this element’s “-metry,” often used for volumetric analysis. This element’s namesake “clock” reaction involves its interconversion between elemental and negatively charged ionic forms. This element is found in Lugol’s solution, which is used to detect starches in solution. This heaviest diatomic element normally sublimes to form a violet-colored gas. For 10 points, name this heaviest stable halogen. ","answer":"ANSWER: iodine [or I] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"5. An Austro-Hungarian monarch with this name was stabbed to death in Geneva by the Italian anarchist Luigi Lucheni. St. Petersburg’s Winter Palace was built by a monarch of this name who led Russia into the Seven Years War. Another monarch with this name claimed to possess the “heart and stomach of a king,” despite her “weak and feeble body,” in the Tilbury Speech. That monarch with this name employed the spymaster Francis Walsingham, who helped her survive the Ridolfi and Babbington plots. For 10 points, give this name of a “Virgin Queen” whose navy defeated the Spanish Armada. ","answer":"ANSWER: Elizabeth [or Elizabeth I; or Empress Elizabeth of Russia; or Empress Elisabeth of Austria] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"6. In this novel, a woman observes that happiness is “but the occasional episode in a general drama of pain” after she learns that the protagonist asked to be buried in an unconsecrated grave. After Joshua Jopp leaks his love letters, the title character of this novel is subjected to a skimmington ride with his lover Lucetta Le Sueur. When the title character goes bankrupt, he is forced to sell his grain business to his former accountant Donald Farfrae. The title character swears off alcohol after drunkenly selling his wife and child to a sailor for five guineas. For 10 points, Michael Henchard appears in what Thomas Hardy novel about a disgraced town official? ","answer":"ANSWER: The Mayor of Casterbridge "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"7. The tremolo-heavy “glide guitar” style of a musician from this non-US country is featured in a song that begins with the lyrics “when I look at you/ oh, I don’t know what’s real.” “When You Sleep” appears on Loveless, the 1991 masterpiece of a band from this country credited with popularizing shoegaze. A singer from this country describes “broken bottles under children’s feet” and “bodies strewn across the dead-end street” in a song that begins with the statement “I can’t believe the news today.” A band from this country recorded the hit songs “Pride (In The Name of Love)” and “Sunday, Bloody Sunday.” For 10 points, name this country where Bono founded U2 in Dublin. ","answer":"ANSWER: Ireland "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"8. An essay by Jonathan Parry examines the role of these things in Hindu rituals. An essay claims that these things have a personality or spirit described by the Polynesian terms hau and mana. The alliance theory of Claude Lévi-Strauss describes women as the “supreme” of these things. One thinker claimed these things were a “total prestation,” meaning that reciprocity was actually obligatory to their use. The Pacific Northwest tradition of potlatch and the Trobriand islanders’ kula ring are two different customs in which these things are exchanged. For 10 points, Marcel Mauss’ magnum-opus is titled for what type of item that is given without an expected return or payment? ","answer":"ANSWER: gifts [accepts equivalents like presents] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"9. This ruler feuded with Pope Vigilius during the Three-Chapter controversy. Victories at Tricamarum and Ad Decimum helped this ruler depose Gelimer and retake control of North Africa from the Vandals. An angry mob crowned Hypatius as emperor during a riot against this ruler that began as a scuffle between Blues and Greens in the Hippodrome. This ruler, who faced the Nika Revolt, employed Tribonian to write the Corpus Juris Civilis. Procopius’ Secret History chronicles how this ruler jockeyed for power with his general Belisarius and his consort Teodora. For 10 points, name this Byzantine emperor who built the Hagia Sophia and issued a namesake law code. ","answer":"ANSWER: Justinian I [or Justinian the Great; prompt on partial answer] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"0. Early work in this technology was spearheaded by Henry Fox Talbot, who introduced a process in which potassium bromide was used to wash paper coated with silver iodide called the calotype. Its inventor is widely considered to be the Frenchman Nicephore Niepce [“nee-say-for NEE-epps”]. Another early form of this technology, which involved a silver-copper plate reacting with mercury vapor, is named for Louis Daguerre. Processes involved in this technology may produce negatives that are printed to reverse coloration. For 10 points, George Eastman popularized the use of what type of technology marketed by Polaroid and Kodak? ","answer":"ANSWER: photography [or photographs; accept any answer referring to cameras; accept photographic film; prompt on pictures or images or film] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"1. A hunchbacked bandleader who played this instrument recorded “A-Tisket, A-Tasket” with Ella Fitzgerald. Chick Webb played this instrument, as did a bandleader known for performing a medley of Leonard Bernstein’s West Side Story. The hard bop album Moanin’ was recorded by a player of this instrument and his “Jazz Messengers.” Dave Brubeck wrote “Take Five” to showcase Joe Morello’s ability on this instrument. With bass, guitar, and piano, this instrument makes up a typical jazz rhythm section. For 10 points, Art Blakey and Buddy Rich played what percussion instrument, which requires sticks? ","answer":"ANSWER: drums [prompt on percussion; prompt on specific kinds of drums, like snare drum or bass drum] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"2. Karl Barth’s book The Epistle to the Romans cites this philosopher’s notion of the “infinite qualitative distinction.” A text by this philosopher uses Mozart’s operas as an example of the musical-erotic and distinguishes between the views of Don Juan and Faust. This philosopher of a Concluding Unscientific Postscript divided life into aesthetic, ethical, and religious stages. He discussed the “teleological suspension of the ethical” in a text that uses the example of Abraham’s willingness to sacrifice Isaac as an example of the “Knight of Faith.” For 10 points, name this Danish philosopher of Either/Or and Fear and Trembling. ","answer":"ANSWER: Søren Kierkegaard [prompt on Johannes de Silentio or Johannes Climacus] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"3. This author wrote a novel about Eve Frame’s disintegrating marriage to the radio actor “Iron Rimm” shortly after his own contentious divorce with Claire Bloom. Another novel by this author of I Married a Communist is framed as a conversation between the protagonist and his psychoanalyst Dr. Spielvogel. Many of this author’s works are set in and around his hometown of Newark, New Jersey and are narrated by his recurring character Nathan Zuckerman. The title character of this author’s first major novel recounts his sexual escapades, which feature a woman known as “The Monkey” and a piece of liver. For 10 points, name this author of Portnoy’s Complaint. ","answer":"ANSWER: Philip Roth "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"5. During this presidential election, South Carolina’s Red Shirts implemented the Mississippi Plan to intimidate black voters, leading to the election of Wade Hampton as governor. After this election, Joseph Bradley was controversially appointed to fill Justice David Davis’ spot on a committee. Despite the release of the Mulligan Letters, James G. Blaine was the frontrunner for this election’s Republican nomination until Roscoe Conkling engineered his defeat. The result of this election was confirmed by the Electoral Commission and settled by a compromise that ended Reconstruction in the South. For 10 points, name this election in which Samuel Tilden lost to Rutherford B. Hayes. ","answer":"ANSWER: election of 1876 [prompt on ‘76] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"6. A passage that describes this figure without naming him states that he “stood poised on the higher horizon, drew near and suspended hung, two bow-lengths away.” During one event, this figure took a man to a tree at the end of the seventh layer of heaven, called the Sidrat al-Muntaha, that this figure could not pass. This figure commanded a man to recite, “Read! In the name of your Lord, who has created all that exists” in a cave on Mount Hira. This figure, who brought the horse Buraq to Muhammad during the Night Journey, will blow a trumpet blast when Jesus returns to Earth. For 10 points, name this archangel who revealed the Quran to Muhammad and has a namesake horn. ","answer":"ANSWER: Gabriel [or Jibril; or Jibra’il] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"7. While living in this place, a writer used a cerium alloy to whittle light-flints, an experience that writer recalled in the “Cerium” chapter of his memoir The Periodic Table. In a different book, the narrator describes how the “flames” of this place “consumed [his] faith forever” while repeating the phrase “never shall I forget.” After a man in this place asks “where is God?” that narrator imagines replying that God is “hanging here from this gallows.” In a 1960 memoir, this location’s guards shout “men to the left, women to the right” as they separate Eliezer from his mother and sisters. For 10 points, Elie Wiesel’s Night describes the horrors of what Nazi concentration camp in Poland? ","answer":"ANSWER: Auschwitz-Birkenau [prompt on concentration camps] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"8. A piece by this composer for violin and piano opens with a repeated 16th-note, 32nd-rest, 32nd-note rhythm on a melody that begins with the notes [read slowly] G-flat, A-flat, G-flat, A-flat, B-flat. This composer imitated the call of a scarlet tanager in the third movement scherzo of a string quartet that begins with a pentatonic viola solo. This composer of 8 Humoresques for piano included a notable English horn solo in the Largo second movement of his most famous symphony. This composer’s ninth symphony was influenced by the African-American spirituals he encountered on a trip to Iowa. For 10 points, name this Czech composer of the New World Symphony. ","answer":"ANSWER: Antonín (Leopold) Dvořák "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"9. It’s not Kenya, but Frederick Lugard pioneered indirect rule while administering the colony that became this country. The earliest evidence of ironworking in Africa was discovered in this country’s valley of Taruga, which was occupied by the Nok people. After the abolition of slavery, this country’s port of Bonny became a center of the palm oil trade. Royal Dutch Shell’s treatment of this country was protested by Ken Saro-Wiwa. During the late 1960s, this country’s Igbo people seceded to form the breakaway Republic of Biafra. For 10 points, name this country once administered by the British from Lagos. ","answer":"ANSWER: Nigeria "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"0. The production of this compound in the kidney with the aid of 1-alpha-hydroxylase is stimulated by parathyroid hormone. A precursor of this compound called ergosterol is found in the cell membranes of fungi. One form of this compound called cholecalciferol is converted from 7-dehydrocholesterol during a “cutaneous synthesis.” Intestinal absorption of phosphate is increased by this vitamin, whose deficiency may lead to bowed legs and greater susceptibility to fractures in young children. For 10 points, rickets is caused by a deficiency in what vitamin that works to increase calcium uptake in the body and is produced in the skin with the help of sunlight? ","answer":"ANSWER: vitamin D [accept Vitamins D1, D2, or D3] Tiebreaker. An early holder of this position was selected because a dove miraculously landed on his head. Theodora and Marozia of the Theophylacti family installed numerous lovers in this position during a period known as the Pornocracy. After conquering the Exarchate of Ravenna, Pepin the Short donated the land to the holder of this position. In a controversy over the right of investiture, one holder of this position was the recipient of Henry IV’s Walk to Canossa. The holder of this position resided in Avignon during the 14th century “Babylonian Captivity.” For 10 points, name this position held by the Bishop of Rome, who leads the Catholic Church. "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Name this familial relation that titles a photo of Florence Owens Thompson, who forlornly looks into the distance in a Dorothea Lange photo titled for a Migrant [one of these people]. ","answer":"ANSWER: mother [or Migrant Mother; accept equivalents to “mother” like mom] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Sally Mann, who controversially photographed her own children for the book Immediate Family, depicted the aftermath of this event in What Remains. Matthew Brady’s best-known photographs depict this event. ","answer":"ANSWER: the American Civil War "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] This woman photographed a nude, pregnant Demi Moore for the August 1991 Vogue magazine cover. She photographed John Lennon clutching his wife, nude, on the day of Lennon’s death. ","answer":"ANSWER: Annie Leibovitz "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Name this Christina Rossetti poem in which the sisters Laura and Lizzie are tempted by the fruit-selling title creatures, who chant “come buy, come buy!” ","answer":"ANSWER: “Goblin Market” "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] This author heavily edited his sister’s novel The Adventures of David Simple after it was first released. He is more famous for writing about Sophia Western’s foundling love in Tom Jones. ","answer":"ANSWER: Henry Fielding "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Love in a Cold Climate and The American Way of Death were written by the sisters Nancy and Jessica, who shared this surname. Nancy and Jessica’s sister Diana, who also had this surname, was married to the British fascist Oswald Mosley. ","answer":"ANSWER: Mitford sisters "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Name this British Marxist historian who discussed the Invention of Tradition in a book he co-edited with Terence Ranger. He is perhaps best known for a trilogy of works that begins with The Age of Revolution. ","answer":"ANSWER: Eric Hobsbawm "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] The Age of Revolution is the first in Hobsbawm’s trilogy about the “long” version of this century, which Hobsbawm claims began with the French Revolution. The unification of Italy occurred during this century. ","answer":"ANSWER: the 19th century [or the 1800s] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Hobsbawm’s Age of Revolution begins in 1789 and ends in this year. Lajos Kossuth’s failed Hungarian Revolution took place during this year. ","answer":"ANSWER: 1848 [prompt on 48] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Name this mathematical operation. According to the fundamental theorem of calculus, it is the inverse of integration. ","answer":"ANSWER: differentiation [or word forms like differentiating; or taking the derivative; or partial derivative; or similar answers that indicate a derivative] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] At these points, a function’s first partial derivatives are all zero, but it is not a local extremum. They are named for a piece of equipment that curves differently in orthogonal directions. ","answer":"ANSWER: saddle points [prompt on minimax points] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] This matrix, named for a German mathematician, contains all of a function’s second-order partial derivatives. It is equal to the transpose of the Jacobian of a function’s gradient. ","answer":"ANSWER: Hessian matrix "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Name this island, called “the Galapagos of the Indian Ocean” due to its diversity of unique flora. ","answer":"ANSWER: Socotra "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] This country officially governs Socotra, although the island has been practically annexed by the UAE following the outbreak of civil war in this country. Houthi forces control its capital city, Sana’a. ","answer":"ANSWER: Yemen "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] The UAE’s presence on Socotra could be used to gain power over shipping through this gulf to Socotra’s west, a major route for oil tankers. This gulf separates Yemen from Somalia and is named for a Yemeni city. ","answer":"ANSWER: Gulf of Aden [or Gulf of Berbera] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] An essay by this author characterizes literary heroes as either Don Quixote or Hamlet depending on their decisiveness. A conflicted party guest is nicknamed the “Hamlet of the Shchigrovsky District” in a story from this author’s Sportsman’s Sketches. ","answer":"ANSWER: Ivan Sergeyevich Turgenev "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"5. ","answer":"ANSWER: Miguel de Cervante "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] This member of Spain’s Generation of ‘98 attempted to interpret Don Quixote independently of Cervantes’ influence in his essay “Our Lord Don Quixote.” He’s better known for novels like Abel Sanchez and Niebla. ","answer":"ANSWER: Miguel de Unamuno "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Many scientists believe that this monotreme species secretes venom from its hind limbs for the purpose of competing for mates, and not as defense against predators. ","answer":"ANSWER: duck-billed platypus [or Ornithorhynchus anatinus] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] The slow loris is believed to be only venomous member of this taxonomic order. Other members of this order include lemurs, chimpanzees, and quiz bowl players. ","answer":"ANSWER: primates "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] The “northern short-tailed” and “American short-tailed” variety of these mole-like mammals are both venomous. Their “Etruscan” variety is considered the smallest mammal by mass. ","answer":"ANSWER: shrews [or Soricidae; or northern short-tailed shrew; or American short-tailed shrew; or Etruscan shrew] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Name these vehicles that were recalled en masse in 2016 due to a glitch that caused their battery packs to overheat and catch on fire. ","answer":"ANSWER: hoverboards [or self-balancing scooters] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Marty McFly rides a hoverboard in the second installment of this film series, whose first film sees Marty and Doc Brown travel to the 1950s in a time-travelling Delorean. ","answer":"ANSWER: Back to the Future "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] In Back to the Future II, this bully travels back in time to give himself a sports almanac, which his past self uses to become a Donald Trump-esque gambling mogul. ","answer":"ANSWER: Biff Tannen [accept either underlined portion] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Give this term for an event in which God reveals himself to a human being. This term with a Greek origin is an alternate name for the feast of Epiphany. ","answer":"ANSWER: theophany "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] This apostle converted to Christianity after Jesus spoke to him on the road to Damascus. His attempts to convert Gentiles are the primary subject of the book of Acts. ","answer":"ANSWER: Saint Paul of Tarsus [or Saul of Tarsus] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] In Acts, the Holy Spirit descends upon the Apostles on this feast day, causing them to speak in tongues. This holy day occurs seven weeks after Easter. ","answer":"ANSWER: Pentecost [or White Sunday or Whitsunday] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Identify this object used by a KGB agent to fire a poisonous ricin pellet at Georgi Markov in London. ","answer":"ANSWER: an umbrella "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Markov was exiled from this communist country during the rule of dictator Todor Zhivkov. Zhivkov came to prominence as the police chief in its capital city, Sofia. ","answer":"ANSWER: Bulgaria "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"1. ","answer":"ANSWER: Turks [or Turkish] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Name this character who titles a novel narrated by John Wheelwright. He dies while protecting a group of Vietnamese children from a grenade at an airport. ","answer":"ANSWER: Owen Meany [prompt on Meany] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] A Prayer for Owen Meany was written by an author with this surname. A much earlier author with this surname wrote the short stories “The Legend of Sleepy Hollow” and “Rip Van Winkle.” ","answer":"ANSWER: Irving [accept John Irving or Washington Irving] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] In the novel, Owen kills Tabitha while taking part in this activity. An Ernest Thayer poem about this activity notes that “there was no joy in Mudville” after Cooney, Barrows, and Casey failed at this activity. ","answer":"ANSWER: baseball "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Name this home state of the Regionalist painter John Steuart Curry. Curry’s mural Tragic Prelude, which depicts a giant bearded man clutching a rifle and bible, is housed in this state’s Capitol Building. ","answer":"ANSWER: Kansas [the first Curry painting mentioned is Baptism in Kansas] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] This other member of the Regionalist movement depicted his native Iowa in a portrait of his sister and dentist, the latter of whom holds a pitchfork, titled American Gothic. ","answer":"ANSWER: Grant Wood "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Wood’s painting Parson Weem’s Fable shows Weems pulling back a curtain to reveal this person as a child, holding an axe. He is also depicted in Gilbert Stuart’s Lansdowne portrait. ","answer":"ANSWER: George Washington "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Name this minister to Louis XVI who published France’s first public budget. He attempted to reform France’s economy during the debt crisis caused by Louis’ decision to finance the American Revolution. ","answer":"ANSWER: Jacques Necker "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Summoned to discuss Necker’s proposed reforms in June 1789, the Third Estate found themselves locked out of their chambers; instead, they moved to this location, usually used for athletic events, where they swore an oath to pursue a constitution. ","answer":"ANSWER: a tennis court [or the Tennis Court Oath] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] A month after the Tennis Court Oath, an angry crowd reacted to Necker’s firing by storming this Parisian prison. ","answer":"ANSWER: the Bastille "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Name these concepts whose origin is attributed to Empedocles. In the dialogue Timaeus, each of these things is associated with a particular Platonic solid. ","answer":"ANSWER: Classical elements [or the four elements] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Timaeus associates this “ever-living” and unstable element with the tetrahedron. Heraclitus considered this to be the fundamental element, unlike Thales, who favored this element’s counterpart, water. ","answer":"ANSWER: fire "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] In contrast to Ionian philosophers, this thinker from Samos believed numbers created harmony in the world. This philosopher, who abstained from eating meat and beans, theorized the “music of the spheres” and the “transmigration of souls.” ","answer":"ANSWER: Pythagoras of Samos "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Name this type of reaction. The Diels-Alder is a 4+2 “cyclo-” type of these reactions. ","answer":"ANSWER: addition reaction [accept cycloaddition] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] In the Michael addition, one of these species, such as a carbanion, attacks the carbonyl compound. Organolithium reagents and anions can be examples of these species, which attack positively charged atoms. ","answer":"ANSWER: nucleophiles "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] The carbanion in the Michael addition has this charge. Halides also possess a charge of this negative number. ","answer":"ANSWER: -1 [or negative one; do not accept or prompt on “one”] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Name this goddess who emerged from the churning of the ocean sitting in a lotus plant. On the third night of Diwali, people light diyas and offer puja to welcome this goddess into their homes. ","answer":"ANSWER: Lakshmi [or Laxmi] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Lakshmi is the consort of Vishnu in this religion, the majority religion in India. Texts from this religion include the Vedas and the Bhagavad Gita. ","answer":"ANSWER: Hinduism "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Lakshmi’s mount Olooka is one of these animals. In Greek myth, Demeter turned Ascalaphus into one of these animals out of anger following Hades’ abduction of Persephone. ","answer":"ANSWER: an owl [prompt on bird] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Name this piece in which the solo trumpet plays a motif with the notes (read slowly) B-flat, low C-sharp, high E, long E-flat, low C. According to the composer’s program notes, this piece’s strings represent “The Silence of the Druids.” ","answer":"ANSWER: The Unanswered Question "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] The Unanswered Question was written by this American composer of the Concord Sonata and Three Places in New England. ","answer":"ANSWER: Charles Ives "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Ives composed a set of Variations on “My Country, ‘Tis of Thee” for this instrument, which Ives played. Players of this large keyboard instrument use a pedalboard to manipulate the sound produced by a set of pipes. ","answer":"ANSWER: pipe organ "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Name this Native American tribe that was subjected to the largest execution in US history after an uprising led by its chief Little Crow. ","answer":"ANSWER: Dakota [or Sioux; do not accept or prompt on “Lakota” or “Nakota”] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] This president commuted the death sentences of many of the captured Dakota warriors. This president, who served as a militia captain during Black Hawk’s War, opened up Indian Territory to white settlers by signing the Homestead Act. ","answer":"ANSWER: Abraham Lincoln "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] The Dakota War took place in this modern-day US state. Little Crow and his tribe resided on land that is now this state’s capital, St. Paul. ","answer":"ANSWER: Minnesota "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Name this medieval Japanese text. Written by lady-in-waiting Sei Shonagon, it contains lists of “Irritating Things” and “Pleasant Things.” ","answer":"ANSWER: the Pillow Book [or Makura no Soshi] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Authors like Ze’ami Motokiyo pioneered this form of medieval Japanese drama, similar to kabuki, in which short farces called kyogen are interspersed with more serious plays. Its performers typically wear masks. ","answer":"ANSWER: Noh [or Nogaku] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] This Lady Murasaki work, written during Japan’s Heian period, is often considered the first modern novel. The title character of this novel is a womanizing prince who falls in love with Lady Fujitsubo. ","answer":"ANSWER: Tale of Genji [or Genji-monogatari] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Name this law in fluid mechanics. It states that the pressure drop of a fluid is proportional to the product of the pipe length times mu times flow rate, divided by pi times pipe radius to the fourth power. ","answer":"ANSWER: Hagen–Poiseuille [“PWAH-zoo-ee”] equation or law "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] The mu term in Poiseuille’s equation represents the dynamic type of this physical quantity. This property quantifies a fluid’s resistance to shear or tensile stress. ","answer":"ANSWER: dynamic viscosity "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Poiseuille’s law is only valid for fluids that are incompressible and have this property. In these fluids, which include water, air, and glycerol, viscosity is independent of shear rates. ","answer":"ANSWER: Newtonian fluids Tiebreaker. This woman says that she has been “a stranger in [her] own land” because of her “father and brother.” For 10 points each: "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Name this character who defies King Creon in order to give her brother Polynices the proper funeral rites. Haemon is devastated when this character hangs herself in a cave at the end of the play she appears in. ","answer":"ANSWER: Antigone [an-TIG-uh-nee] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Antigone is one of this classical Greek playwright’s Theban plays, which also include Oedipus Rex and Oedipus at Colonus. ","answer":"ANSWER: Sophocles "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] This twentieth century French playwright adapted Sophocles’ Antigone in a staging designed to parallel the Vichy France regime. In his Antigone, tragedy is defined as “a film without a sound track.” ","answer":"ANSWER: Jean Anouilh [ah-noo-EEL] EXTRA Arthur Anderson and Charles Dibble made the first full English translation of this 12-book work after it was rediscovered by the scholar Angelo Bandini. For 10 points each: "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Name this text preserved in the Laurentian library. It was composed by the missionary Bernardino de Sahagun in conjunction with his students in Tlatelolco. ","answer":"ANSWER: Florentine Codex [prompt on partial answer] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] The Florentine Codex is one of the major sources on this empire’s practices, which included human sacrifices under rulers like Montezuma II. ","answer":"ANSWER: Aztec Empire "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] This interpreter to the conquistador Hernán Cortés appears in many of the Florentine Codex’ illustrations. Her child by Cortés, Martín, is considered one of Mexico’s first mestizos. ","answer":"ANSWER: La Malinche [or Doña Marina] This solid figure is represented by the Schläfli symbol {3,5}, and its volume equals roughly 8.66 times its edge length squared. For 10 points each: "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Name this solid whose four-dimensional analog is considered to be the hexacosichoron, or 600-cell. ","answer":"ANSWER: regular icosahedron "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Because the icosahedron is a convex, regular polyhedron, it is one of these five “solids” named for an ancient Greek thinker. ","answer":"ANSWER: Platonic solids "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] The icosahedron is considered a dual to this other Platonic solid, which is made up of pentagonal faces. ","answer":"ANSWER: regular dodecahedron The study introducing this test also asked children for etymologies of words like “blackboard.” “Thanksgiving.” and “Friday.” For 10 points each: "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Name this linguistic test introduced by Jean Berko Gleason in which participants asked to provide a plural form to describe a pair of a fictional bird-like creature. ","answer":"ANSWER: Wug test "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Gleason conducted the wug test to examine the ability of these people to learn morphological rules. According to one hypothesis, these individuals are able to acquire language because they haven’t left the “critical period.” ","answer":"ANSWER: children [accept equivalents] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"K","question":"[10] Lydia White has done research on how this concept contributes to second language acquisition. Noam Chomsky put forth the “poverty of the stimulus” argument to argue for this theory, which suggests that certain structures and constraints are innate to all language. ","answer":"ANSWER: universal grammar [or UG]"}]
